<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>AM207</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/</id><updated>2014-01-28T11:13:50-05:00</updated><entry><title>Lecture 0</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/blog/lecture-0.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-28T11:13:50-05:00</updated><author><name>Pavlos Protopapas</name></author><id>tag:iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207,2014-01-28:blog/lecture-0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h1 id="why-taking-this-class"&gt;Why taking this class ?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not on Friday&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not on Monday&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get a free lecture after every 5 you attend&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not early in the morning&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you do not understand you can blame it on my accent&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will give candy on Valentine's day&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No more insomnia, I will make sure you get 1.5 hour sleep&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You are required to have your computer in class so you can tweet, facebook, chat and all that for free&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The coolest class name "Advanced Scientific Computing: Stochastic Optimization Methods. Monte Carlo Methods for Inference and Data Analysis"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You will learn useful skills for survival&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h1 id="mr.-anderson-survival-skills-am207.-a-preview-what-is-coming"&gt;Mr. Anderson, survival skills AM207. A preview what is coming&lt;/h1&gt;
The story begins in 1981. Mr Anderson was traveling on a twin engine for the richness of South America. His brother, Jeffrey, has made a lot of money finding gold on the Andean mountains. Jeffrey was the adventurous type, he dropped out of high school and followed a friend who was going down to South America. He returned back in 10 years a very rich man. Mr Anderson, stayed at school and then went to one of the most prestigious universities in North America, Harvard, where he studied computational science under the famous Prof Provlief. These studies never got Mr Anderson any money, fame or even popularity. He was a loner, shy and very uncomfortable with people he did not know. What nowadays people may may call a nerd, back then people called them peculiar.
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img align="middle" src="images/harvard.jpeg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After graduating from Harvard, he took odd jobs at different place in Boston but none of them satisfied his curiosity or his intellect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he heart that the mining companies in the desert of Atacama were looking for bright young people to uncover the reaches of nitrite , since he had a very good understanding of engineering and mathematics he decided to take the risk and go down there.&lt;/p&gt;
After a long trip to Lima, Peru, he boarded a twin engine that would take him to San Pedro in the middle of the desert, driest place on earth; even lizards dried out here. Half way through the trip they were crossing a high pass of the Andes and over the desert. He could see down from his window the infinite desert. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img align="middle" src="images/TwinEngine.png" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt; It was then when he realized that one of the engines was on fire. He informed the pilot, who told him not to worry and they could continue on the other engine. But all of the sudden the other engine stopped operating. The pilot was quick to jump out of the plane with the only one chute that was available. Anderson was ready to die, sat on the seat and simply came to the conclusion that life was all about luck. He remembered the words his professor telling him about &lt;strong&gt;randomness&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/atacama.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; The plane went down very fast and luckily landed on the soft sand. Mr. Anderson survived despite the odds. &lt;strong&gt;"There is always that small probability and if you do not simulate things well, you will miss those outliers"&lt;/strong&gt;, he remembered his wise professor telling him. He was so right, he thought.&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He got out of the plane, dusted himself off, happily concluded that nothing was broken and he survived a plane crash, he started examining the surrounding. There was absolutely nothing around. No water no food. I will not survive, he thought. The voice of his professor was in his head though. "There is always that small little probability, the world is &lt;strong&gt;ergotic&lt;/strong&gt; and if you search hard and smart enough you can get everywhere. " Wish now he new what ergotic meant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He took the GPS device (an old version of GPS) and started walking west hoping he could get to the coast. He knew the coast was hundred of kilometers away but he tried to use any information he had to his benefit. He also took with him all medical supplies and whatever else he could get.&lt;/p&gt;
After 3 hours of walking, exhausted, thirsty and about to collapse he saw something like a water. He run and indeed, there was a little pond. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/lake.jpeg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br/&gt;'How lucky I am', he thought. He was ready to drink when he realized that there was a sign "Poison, do not drink". He looked into the medical supplies for he remembered there was something resembling antidote for poisonous water.&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/poison.jpg" width="100"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got it out and read the instructions. One drop per cubic meter of water. Do not use more. Excess use can have severe side effects, such as blindness. Mr. Anderson has to calculate the volume of the water. Luckily the pond seem to have a constant depth of about the length of his palm, which he knew it was 30cm. He knew he had to calculate the volume of the water in the pond. How though? Now he remembers what he learned back in Harvard under professor Provlief. He form a square on the sand using his body as a measuring stick, throw stones in the air and by measuring the number of stones that landed in the water vs the total number of stones he was able to calculate the area of the pong and therefore the volume of the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(A_{pond} = \frac{N_{in}}{N_{total}} A\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He continued his westward directions, however all of sudden a sand storm started and visibility became very limited; he could not see anything now and had hard time breathing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/desert-survival-8.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He knew if he could go at the highest point he would have a much better chance in surviving. But without seeing the task of finding the highest point was impossible. Luckily again, his old professor has taught him how to find the maximum in a parameter space, which seemed to be perfectly appropriate for his situation. Remembering his professor's explanation, he stepped in a random direction and feeling if he went up or down. If he stepped downwards he reserved his position and tried again otherwise he continue from the new position. Also he remembered from his lectures that every now and then he should be accepting bad positions, or going downwards in order to avoid local maxima. Following this procedure, three hours later her was able to be at the high ground and saved his life once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/mcmc.png" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He stayed at the high ground for a while until the sand storm passed. Unfortunately, now it was cloudy and he could not see the sun and during the sand storm he lost his sense of directionality. He had the old GPS but also found a pedometer that could provide him with estimates of his speed and with some basic astronomy he knew he could approximately find the direction. Started walking westward he faced the dilemma. Should he be trusting the old GPS or should he be trusting the pedometer and his estimations? All of sudden he remembered Prof. Provlief lectures on Kalman filters. He remembered that this was a way to find out which one to believe more. Using the Kalman's gain he was able to maintain course and in few hours of walking he saw in the far lights of a little village.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\hat{X}_k = K_k \, Z_k +(1-K_k) \hat{X}_{k-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/kalman_filter.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am saved he thought. He started running towards the lights but when he arrived closer, he realized that this was not civilization as he was hoping for. This was a small dwelling out in the country with few people sitting around the fire playing a game. They looked like outlaws, certainly not to be trusted. He had no other choice but to approach them. He was hungry, tired, did not sleep or had water for few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/outlaws.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Anderson asked for water but the characters of the camp told him that in the desert nobody gives you water; you have to earn it. Next they invited him to join them in a game of dudo, a game similar to poker but played with dice. Mr Anderson knew nothing of the game but quickly realized that it is all based on probability theory. After few rounds, he realized that all the players were calculating probabilities where the game is based on commutative probability and extreme value distributions. Thanks to a little project he did with Prof. Provlief he had a small computer program using Markov Chain Monte Carlo to calculate complicated integrals of probability distributions. Luckily he had on his Texas Instrument calculator the program that he used for the project. Quickly he modified the code and soon after he started to win round after round. Winner of the game, he left the camp with water, food and a horse, feeling good about himself and all the time he spent with Prof. Provleif. Again it saved his life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/perudo.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
On the horse now, he continued his journey trying to get out of the desert and still determined to make a lot of money before returning home. After a day of riding he came upon a little mining village. He was so happy to eventually be in a place he could take a hot meal and a bath. Rest and continue on his quest to become rich. He checked into a local hotel and went for dinner at a local bar called the empanadillas caliente. Sat down on the bar next to a big strong man, Mr. Jimenez was his name. He asked him what he was doing and he told him that he was a mining engineer looking for iodine. Apparently there was a lot of demand because of the expanding business of photography and iodine was used in films. Mr Jimenez was looking to find ways to extract iodine from nitrate only to be failing. He explained the problem as mixed pools of nitrate and iodine but nobody knew how to find where the pools were. They only had sonars that they used to find the core but could not distinguish between the two. After couple of piscos, he again remembered the lectures of Prof. Provlief about expectation maximization and how one can find out the values of things not directly observed but can be deduced. He continued conversing with Mr. Jimenez and quickly realized that the methods he learned can be applied here. This led to a vivid discussion between two technically savvy people while consuming a lot of piscos. By the morning they have figured out the likelihood function and on his little calculator he was able to run the code and estimate the amount of iodine vs nitrate on different possible reservoirs.
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/EM.jpeg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next few months they worked intensively to perfect the method and started a new company in the exploration of iodine. Their new company started making money and soon Mr. Anderson had enough money to feel good about things. His dream was coming together - eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/washing.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately his relation with Mr. Jimenez went bad after the first few months. it turned out that Mr Jimenez was not so honest with his dealing and he made Mr. Anderson signed a contract without paying attention assuming that Mr. Jimenez was his friend. At the end he ended with few dozen thousand dollars and out of the company. Totally disappointed but at least with a little cash he took the first plane out of South America to London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="picture"&gt;
&lt;img src="images/london-attractions.jpg" width="400"&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing he hit the local pub. There he met Mr. Muray who was working at a financial firm in equaty trading. Mr. Anderson and Mr. Muray become friends over a warm beer at the pub. Mr Muray was talking about how trading was done and again he connected back to Prof. Provlief lectures on Hidden Markov Models and how to simulate sequential events of hidden variables. Quickly he pulled his little computer and started calculating. Long story short he is now a multimillioner trading on wall street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell vbox"&gt;
&lt;div class="input hbox"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
In []:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="input_area box-flex1"&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="lectures"></category></entry><entry><title>Homeworks and homework policies</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/blog/homeworks-and-homework-policies.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-27T23:00:40-05:00</updated><author><name>Pavlos Protopapas</name></author><id>tag:iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207,2014-01-27:blog/homeworks-and-homework-policies.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h4&gt;Homework Schedule&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There will be 10 problem sets during the semester. Problem sets are handed out weekly (on Thursday, after class) and are due the following Wednesday, at 11.59PM, unless otherwise announced.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Homework Policies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of the assignments is to develop your computational skills while learning the essential stochastic methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be handing in homeworks as Ipython notebooks. Your ipython notebook should be runnable from beginning to end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should hand in one solution per person, but you are encouraged to work in groups of three or less for the homework and final project. Collaboration means you work together; it does not mean you split the work. Each student is expected to work on all homeworks and all questions. All code should be your own.
 
An ISite with a dropbox will be provided for your homework and project submissions. The dropbox for each homework and project will close on the deadline for that piece of work. NO work will be accepted after the deadline. Do not submit in the last seconds before the dropbox closes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We understand, however, that medical factors may occasionally interfere with your ability to participate or to hand in work on time. If that factor is an extenuating circumstance, we will ask you to provide documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you believe there is an error in your assignment grading, please submit an explanation via email to us  within 3 days of receiving the grade. No regrade requests will be accepted orally, and no regrade requests will be accepted more than 3 days after you receive the grade for the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="homeworks"></category></entry><entry><title>Schedule of Lectures</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/blog/schedule-of-lectures.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-27T22:33:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Pavlos Protopapas</name></author><id>tag:iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207,2014-01-27:blog/schedule-of-lectures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A tentative schedule can be seen &lt;a href="{filename}/../../schedule.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="lectures"></category></entry><entry><title>Installing Python</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/blog/installing-python.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-27T22:30:33-05:00</updated><author><name>Rahul Dave</name></author><id>tag:iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207,2014-01-27:blog/installing-python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;All the labs and homeworks in this course are Python-based. This page provides information about configuring Python on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 0&lt;/strong&gt; 
The IPython notebook runs in the browser, and works best in Google Chrome. You probably want to use Chrome for assignments in this course&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Recommended Method: Anaconda&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anaconda Python distribution is an easily-installable bundle of Python and many of the libraries used throughout this class. It includes numpy/scipy/matplotlib/pandas/scikit-learn and other numerical libraries. Unless you have a good reason not to, we recommend that you use Anaconda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Mac/Linux users&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="http://continuum.io/downloads"&gt;appropriate version&lt;/a&gt; of Anaconda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the instructions on that page to run the installer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test it out: open a terminal window, and type &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt;, you should see something like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Python&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;2.7.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.6.1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x86_64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Jun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;28&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2013&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;code&gt;Anaconda&lt;/code&gt; doesn't appear on the first line, you are using a different version of Python. See the troubleshooting section below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test out the IPython notebook: open a Terminal window, and type &lt;code&gt;ipython notebook&lt;/code&gt;. A new browser window should pop up. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;New Notebook&lt;/code&gt; to create a new notebook file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update IPython to the newest version by typing &lt;code&gt;conda update ipython&lt;/code&gt; at the command line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Windows Users&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href="http://continuum.io/downloads"&gt;appropriate version&lt;/a&gt; of Anaconda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the instructions on that page to run the installer. This will create a directory at &lt;code&gt;C:\Anaconda&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test it out: start the Anaconda launcher, which you can find in &lt;code&gt;C:\Anaconda&lt;/code&gt; or, in the Start menu. Start the IPython notebook. A new browser window should open. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;New Notebook&lt;/code&gt;, which should open a new page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update IPython to the newest version by opening a command prompt, and typing &lt;code&gt;conda update ipython&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Opening IPython Notebooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To view an IPython notebook, you must first start the IPython notebook server in the directory where the file lives. Simply navigate to this directory at the command prompt, and type &lt;code&gt;ipython notebook&lt;/code&gt;. This will open a browser window, listing all the &lt;code&gt;ipynb&lt;/code&gt; files in that directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt;
When you start python, you don't see a line like &lt;code&gt;Python 2.7.5 |Anaconda 1.6.1 (x86_64)|&lt;/code&gt;. You are using a Mac or Linux computer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason&lt;/strong&gt;
You are most likely running a different version of Python, and need to modify your Path (the list of directories your computer looks through to find programs). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution&lt;/strong&gt;
Find a file like &lt;code&gt;.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;.profile&lt;/code&gt;. Open the file in a text editor, and add a line at this line at the end: &lt;code&gt;export PATH="$HOME/anaconda/bin:$PATH"&lt;/code&gt;. Close the file, open a new terminal window, type &lt;code&gt;source ~/.profile&lt;/code&gt; (or whatever file you just edited). Type &lt;code&gt;which python&lt;/code&gt; -- you should see a path that points to the anaconda directory. If so, running &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; should load the proper version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this doesn't work (typing &lt;code&gt;which python&lt;/code&gt; doesn't point to anaconda), you might be using a different shell. Type &lt;code&gt;echo $SHELL&lt;/code&gt;. If this isn't &lt;code&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt;, you need to edit a different startup file (for example, if if &lt;code&gt;echo $SHELL&lt;/code&gt; gives &lt;code&gt;$csh&lt;/code&gt;, you need to edit your &lt;code&gt;.cshrc&lt;/code&gt; file. The syntax for this file is slightly different: &lt;code&gt;set PATH = ($HOME/anaconda/bin $PATH)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt;
You are running the right version of python (see above item), but are unable to import numpy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason&lt;/strong&gt;
You are probably loading a different copy of numpy that is incompatible with Anaconda&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution&lt;/strong&gt;
See the above item to find your &lt;code&gt;.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.profile&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file. Open it, and add the line &lt;code&gt;unset PYTHONPATH&lt;/code&gt; at the end. Close the file, open a new terminal window, type &lt;code&gt;source ~/.profile&lt;/code&gt; (or whatever file you just edited), and try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt;
Under Windows, you receive an error message similar to the following: "'pip' is not recognized as an internal or external command, operable program or batch file."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reason&lt;/strong&gt;
The correct Anaconda paths might not be present in your PATH variable, or Anaconda might not have installed correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution&lt;/strong&gt;
Ensure the Anaconda directories to your path environment variable ("\Anaconda" and "\Anaconda\Scripts").  See &lt;a href="http://superuser.com/questions/284342/what-are-path-and-other-environment-variables-and-how-can-i-set-or-use-them"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this does not correct the problem, reinstall Anaconda.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="homeworks"></category><category term="labs"></category></entry><entry><title>Schedule of Labs</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/blog/schedule-of-labs.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-26T15:21:38-05:00</updated><author><name>Rahul Dave</name></author><id>tag:iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207,2014-01-26:blog/schedule-of-labs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will have 12 labs during the semester given on Friday at 11:00am-12:30pm. The goal of the labs is to go through some real world problems while reviewing the material from class. The labs will be helpful in doing the homework: you are strongly encouraged to attend. Since the lab also does real world applications, it will help you do your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python numerical stack tutorial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frequentist examples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Priors, how, what and when &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MCMC on the cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gibbs on steroids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;r u NUTS? More on Hamiltonian MC &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The art of motorcycle maintenance and SA &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GA for the masses &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stockwits. Predicting the financial market using sentiment analysis and Sequential Monte Carlo &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CO2 prediction. Gaussian Process application &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All you wanted to know about PGM &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(If time permits) Dynamic Bayesian Averaging. Various applications and examples &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="labs"></category></entry><entry><title>Projects and project policies</title><link href="http://iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207/blog/projects-and-project-policies.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-26T15:21:29-05:00</updated><author><name>Pavlos Protopapas</name></author><id>tag:iacs-courses.seas.harvard.edu/courses/am207,2014-01-26:blog/projects-and-project-policies.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h4&gt;Project Schedule&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet to be determined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Project Policies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the homework there will be a final project. The final project will be done over a period of 5 weeks, the first two of which will be concommitant with homeworks. In these two weeks, you will be expected to come up with and submit a proposal for the final project. There will be no homework for the last three weeks of the course, so as to provide you ample time to work on your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be expected to produce a written paper and a poster to showcase your project. All code used for the project must also be submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dropbox for the project will close on the deadline for that piece of work. NO work will be accepted after the deadline. Do not submit in the last seconds before the dropbox closes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="projects"></category></entry></feed>